Hello everybody. I hope this video comes
as a nice welcome surprise. Welcome to
AP Calculus Unit 1. Now, I want to be
very, very clear here. For the past
year, I covered the entire AP
pre-calculus course on this channel. And
I did this because it was the highest
level of math I have ever taken. But
now, I have received literal hundreds of
comments begging for me to review this
stupidly long course. So, here I am only
deciding to do 10 unit review videos
that are required. Just so you were
aware, I have had to teach myself this
course to be able to make these videos.
So, all I ask is please just follow my
Instagram. This took weeks to make, man,
please. Anyway, this unit is worth 10 to
12% on the AB exam and 4 to 7% on the BC
exam. I'll just say let's get into it
already. So, I've never really made unit
specific videos before, so I suppose
I'll start this simply. What is
calculus? It is the study of continuous
change. Do you remember back in the
first few topics of pre-calculus where
we covered rate of change and I sounded
like I was at least two wives in? Well,
a lot of that rate of change stuff is
similar to calculus with the same
formula for rate of change over an
interval and also finding rate of change
at a specific point. The big focus of
this unit is limits and a new thing
called continuity. That means I get to
split this video in half. So, welcome to
the limit part of this video. You might
remember we also covered limits in
pre-calculus. So, why don't we zoom in
on what a limit truly is? Let's take the
basic graph f ofx= x. And now let's say
we have the limit as x approaches 3 of f
ofx. A limit is simply about approach.
It is about quote getting close to a
number. So on this graph as x approaches
3 on the y or f ofx we are approaching
positive three. We can take this even
further by taking the plus and minus
limits. Remember minus is approaching
from the left plus is approaching from
the right. So let's see here.
Approaching from the left we would be
approaching three. And approaching from
the right it would also be three. But
this is a pretty easy example. Now let's
do something like this. It is a
peace-wise graph. Now let's answer the
same three limit questions. The limit as
x approaches three from the left is
still three on the y. But as x
approaches three from the right, it is
five. See how these two answers are
completely different. That means the
limit as x approaches three without the
plus or minus just like a girlfriend for
me doesn't exist. This will only happen
when these two are different numbers.
But let me ask you a question. What does
f of three equal? Now I mean yes we see
two places on the y where it is but one
of them is a hole where nothing exists.
So the only right answer here is the
filledin dot which is five. And if you
had a graph like this yes the limit as x
approaches two of the function would be
three but f of two would be five because
that is the filledin point. Now let's
move away from graphs. Time to talk
about a good friend of graphs called
tables. In this case limits are actually
pretty easy to estimate. For example, in
this table, it's pretty obvious that the
limit as x approaches 5 of this function
will be two. And that's pretty much all
I have for tables. Just remember to
always round your answer to three
decimal places. Um, so uh, all right.
Now, I'd like to move to algebra with
limits. I kind of relate this to log
properties because you find there will
be a lot of similarities between them
and the limits. The big foundational
property of limits is the limit of f ofx
plus f ofx would equal the limit of f
ofx plus the limit of f ofx which would
just be 2 * the limit of f ofx. These
evolve into many other properties that
you can try and memorize if you really
want to, but I'd rather just do some
practice problems. Essentially, the
basic thing to know is the limit of a
constant is a constant. So the limit of
1 is equal to 1. And the limit as x
approaches 3 of 1 billion is 1 billion.
So look at this problem. The limit as x
approaches 2 of f of f ofx. Remember
what I said back in pre-calculus. You
start from the inside and go to the
outside. So as x approaches 2, f ofx or
y would approach 1. So now we can fill
that in. Or if you wanted to do correct
notation, you can write this. Then now
we need to find the y value as x
approaches - 1 which is 2. So 2 is our
final answer. What about this problem?
The limit as x approaches 10 of 1 + 9
over 3. Solving the parenthesis we get
4. And remember the limit of a constant
is a constant. So the answer is just
simply four. If we were to manipulate
this as being the limit as x approaches
10 of fx plus g ofx over 3 where the
limit as x approaches 10 of fx= 1 and
the limit as x approaches 10 of g ofx=
9. The answer would still be the same
because we just be plugging in the same
values. What about if you have a
peace-wise function here? The way to
solve it is by plugging in the limit to
each problem. If they match, then that
is the answer. And if they don't match,
just like my girlfriend, the limit
doesn't exist. So now, say we have
limits but with x's in the parenthesis.
If you want to solve the limit, the
basic method you should always try first
is direct substitution. This is where
you plug in whatever x is approaching
for x in the argument and solve it. A
lot of times though, you'll find that
sometimes this will create a zero in the
denominator if it is a rational
function. Obviously that is undefined.
So we need to do something different. So
what do we do here? Simple. We use
algebra. foiling and canceling out
expressions, multiplying by the
conjugate, factoring, you choose really.
As long as you can manipulate the
function to where the denominator won't
equal zero when you do direct
substitution, then it really doesn't
matter what you do. Obviously, if
nothing works and everything you do
seems to only cause a zero in the
denominator, then the likely answer is
that the limit just doesn't exist. Oh,
and there are also these identities you
can use for limits. Just remember that
these are only able to be used if the
limit approaches zero. Let's remember
also that if the limit approaches
infinity or negative infinity, we have
handydandy tricks for polomial functions
in my pre-calculus 1.6 video and the
handydandy tricks for rational functions
in my pre-calculus 1.7 video. Those
videos will both be linked in the
description. Now, let me introduce you
to something that sounds and looks a lot
more complex than it actually is. The
squeeze theorem. The best way I think I
can explain this is with an example.
This one, the limit as x approaches 0 of
x * s of 1 /x. Let's ignore the x for a
second. From trigonometry, I know that a
sign graph falls between the range of -1
and 1. Next, if we bring the x back, we
now have to multiply the outer numbers
by x. So, we get x and negx. So, now
let's write them in their proper limit
form, which we do by simply adding on
the limit as x approaches zero to each
of them. Obviously, we can't do direct
substitution on the middle one because
we'd get zero in the denominator. But we
can do it to the outer ones. For both of
them, we'd simply get zero. So here is
where our squeeze theorem comes in. The
idea is that these numbers are squeezing
the limit in the middle. If these two
numbers are the same, then simply put
the answer is whatever the number is or
in this case zero. If the numbers are
not the same, then the squeeze theorem
cannot be used to find the limit. So say
that you were given functions to solve
for the outer parts of the squeeze
theorem to find an inner function's
limit. If I were to solve those
functions and get different answers,
then simply put, I cannot use the
squeeze theorem to find the limit. All
right, congratulations. We've now
finished with the limits part of the
video and are moving on to the
continuity part. So the basic definition
that teachers give for continuity is
that a graph is continuous if you can
with your pencil trace the entire graph
without having to lift it. Meaning there
is no breaks, jumps or holes. First
let's talk about the three types of
discontinuities. They are removable
discontinuity which is just holes,
vertical asmtote discontinuity and jump
discontinuity. I think holes and
vertical asmmptotes are pretty simple
for you to remember how to find. They
mostly will all come from rational
functions. Holes happen when you cancel
something out. And vertical asmmptotes
happen when functions are in the
denominator that don't cancel out.
Vertical asmmptotes can also appear in
tangent functions if you remember. And
if you want to know how to calculate
them, go watch my pre-calculus video
link in the description. And finally, a
jump discontinuity is actually pretty
simple. This is what it looks like on a
graph. Notice how one function jumps to
the other one. The way to find this in a
peiewise equation is by plugging in the
values in the inequalities. And if they
don't match, there is a jump
discontinuity. Now I want to describe
the math definition for continuity at
one point. Three things have to be true
for one point to be continuous at the
point x= c. f of c has to be defined.
The limit as x approaches c of f ofx has
to exist. And the limit as x approaches
c of f ofx has to equal f of c. Let's
try an example. This peace-wise function
is it continuous at c= 1. First of all,
let's see if f of one is defined. Yes,
it is because it would equal one. Okay.
Next, let's check the second one. The
limit as x approaches one. The way we do
this is by finding the left and right
limits. As x approaches one from the
right side, we would plug in one for
this function and simplifying we'd get
one. Then for the left limit, we
simplify this function and also get one.
Because those two match, the limit does
in fact exist. Okay, so for the third
one, now we need to see if the limit is
equal to f of 1. And yes, it is because
f of 1 is equal to 1. So yes, this
function is continuous at x= 1. But what
if we transition to finding continuity
over an interval instead of just at one
point? This is where you kind of
parallel it with finding domains of
functions. Now, I'm going to trust that
you know how to find the domain of most
functions as you literally are in
calculus. However, I will just offer
some friendly advice. Polomial,
rational, power, exponential,
logarithmic, and trig functions are all
continuous in their domain. Just
remember that rational and log functions
have domain holes because of asmmptotes
along with some trig functions. That
means if you find the domain of these
functions which I hope you already know
how to the functions will be continuous
with its domain. So that means in most
of these questions the answer is simply
the domain. The only place this gets
muddy is with peacewise functions just
like this. Obviously these two functions
on their own are polomials which would
both have domains and continuities of
all real numbers. But let's try
something here and plug in one to each
function. Oh boy, one is one and one is
two. That means there is a jump
discontinuity at x= 1. So the way we'd
write the intervals where the function
is continuous on is by the interval
notation we do for domainative infinity
to 1 with a union and 1 toative
infinity. We don't use brackets anywhere
here because we know at the point x= 1
it is discontinuous. Now let's say we
have a question like this. Let f be a
function defined by fx= x^2 - 1 / x -1.
What is the value of f of 1 if x is
continuous at x= 1? So your immediate
thought here is to expand the numerator,
cancel out the xus one and say there is
a whole or removable discontinuity and
be done and say f of one isn't defined.
But that is not what the question asked.
The question essentially created a
separate realm where the function is
continuous at x= 1. So let's just
algebra this out. We cancel out the x
-1's. Then we plug in one for x in the
function and we get 2 is equal to f of
1. And that is our answer. And last but
not least, I want to introduce you to a
theorem you will likely never use, but
the CED forces me to teach. If your
function is continuous on the interval A
to B, and your target number K is
between the two endpoint values f of A
and F of B, then the function must have
the value of K at least once for some X
between A and B. This is known as the
intermediate value theorem, and it has
three parts to use it. Number one, you
must confirm the function is continuous
on the interval a to b. Number two, you
must make sure that f of a doesn't equal
f of b. And number three, you must check
that k is between f of a and f of b. If
all of those are true, then the number k
will exist within the interval a to b.
And there it is. This unit is done. Not
too hard, right? I hope this course
doesn't get too difficult. But whoa,
whoa, whoa. Don't click off the video
yet. There's a ritual I like to do at
the end of most all of my unit review
videos on this channel, and that is
asking you to watch this video and
subscribe to this channel. It is my non-
educational channel for when I wish to
move away from all this AP stuff. So,
please just subscribe for me, man.
[Music]